All
righty. בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Okay, so today's דף daf is נ"ו
nun-vav officially, where we're on נ"ו עמוד ב'. nun-vav amud bet. We're
going to make a very serious effort and see if we can
catch up. We pick up at the top of נ"ו עמוד ב',
nun-vav amud bet, where it says
והרי הרי חמרין, Vaharei harei chamarin, the donkey drivers, four lines from
the top, and the issue had been that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
allows a woman to be מוחל machel part of the כתובה, ketubah,
so effectively the כתובה ketubah is less than 200 or 100, but
he doesn't allow an initial stipulation for it to start as less
than that. So and that's the גמרא Gemara says why not? He
says that you could even be מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה, matneh
al mah she-katuv ba-Torah, you can even change the parameters of the
monetary aspects of the biblical obligations of the קידושין, kiddushin, שאר sheer
and כסות, kesut, not עונה. onah. So how could he not allow
you to change the rabbinic? And his basic answer is that the
rabbis wanted to strengthen the rabbinic institution of כתובה, ketubah, עשו חיזוק
לדבריהם יותר משל תורה. aso chizuk l'divreihem yoter mishel Torah. So they
wanted to prevent that from being modified even if you could modify
some of the biblical monetary obligations. So now the גמרא Gemara says
the following, הרי חמרין, Harei chamarin, but one minute, there's the case
of the donkey drivers דשכיחי, de-shchichi, which is a common scenario because
we said also that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was only going to
strengthen כתובה ketubah which was common. ולא עבדו רבנן חיזוק, V'lo avdu
rabanan chizuk,
and the rabbis did not reinforce it. דתנן, Detnan, we taught in
the משנה, Mishnah, חמרין שנכנסו לעיר, chamarin shenichnesu l'ir, donkey drivers come
to the city, actually they're also like merchants, and one says, שלי
חדש ושל חברי ישן, sheli chadash v'shel chaveirai yashan,
we had this before. Mine is new grain, this does not mean
because we're going to say this is all rabbinic issue, so this
does not mean the thank you the biblical aspects of חדש, chadash,
but it means just it's new and therefore new is not as
good, it hasn't been as dried out, okay, so mine is of
inferior quality and my friend's here is old.
שלי אינו מתוקן, Sheli eino metukan, mine is not with תרומות ומעשרות
terumos u'maasros separated from it ושל חברי מתוקן, v'shel chaveirai metukan, my
friend's does. אינם נאמנין. Einam ne'emanin. They're not believed, even though you
would say look, he's saying buy from my friend, don't buy from
me, maybe that should give us weight to believe him, but no,
the point is in this city this is what they say and
in the next city they reverse it, so maybe they've got a
whole trick going on here. רבי יהודה אומר נאמנין, Rabbi Yehuda omer
ne'emanin, they are believed. So why is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda prepared
to believe them? It's an issue of דמאי, demai, rabbinically we have
to be concerned that the עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz has not taken
תרומות ומעשרות. terumos u'maasros. Why doesn't he try to protect this rabbinic
institution? Now of course it's a little bit different, I mean we
were dealing with cases about, you know, institutions that created monetary obligations
and to say that he didn't want us to mess with them.
This is a question about an obligation to take תרומות ומעשרות terumos
u'maasros and who can you believe and so on. Not exactly the
same, just because he wants to strengthen, you know, sort of financial
obligations that the rabbis instituted doesn't mean he's going to come to
the defense, you know, of every single rabbinic institution, but nevertheless that's
the גמרא's Gemara question. Let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, ודאי דדבריהם עבדו רבנן חיזוק ספק דדבריהם לא
עבדו רבנן חיזוק. vadai de-divreihem avdu rabanan chizuk, safek de-divreihem lo avdu
rabanan chizuk.
No,
something that was a definite institution like the obligations of the כתובה,
ketubah, the rabbis reinforced and said that you can't modify them, at
least directly, you can only indirectly modify them by being מוחל. machel.
Something that of taking תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'maasros by דמאי, demai, yes
it's a rabbinic institution, but it's because of a doubt, it's because
of a
concern maybe תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'maasros weren't taken and therefore since the
whole thing is based on a question, it's weaker fundamentally and he
had no and he did not want to bother reinforcing it. רבא
אמר דמאי הקילו. Rava amar demai heikilu. רבא Rava says it's not
just a general thing that's based on a doubt, specifically it's דמאי
demai and דמאי demai there are lots of leniencies because by דמאי
demai in principle we really believe that תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'maasros were
taken, so therefore we're going to have lots of leniencies by דמאי.
demai. Bottom line is that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allows you is
not as strict as רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
doesn't even allow the woman to be מוחל machel part of the
כתובה, ketubah, the effective obligation for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir has to
be 200 and 100, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allows a woman to
be מוחל machel but doesn't allow the amount to be modified at
the outset
because even though he allows a person to modify biblical monetary obligations
of the marriage, this rabbinic one he wants to reinforce and therefore
the base obligation has to be there, you have to start with
the 200 and the 100 even if afterwards then the woman could
be מוחל. machel. Now we have
so that was רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda now we go back to
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, I've been saying רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir first,
anyway here's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir in the משנה, Mishnah, רבי מאיר
אומר כל הפוחת, Rabbi Meir omer kol hapocheis, anybody who has less
than 200 for the בתולה betulah and 100 for the אלמנה almanah
is בעילת זנות. be'ilat zenut. Now
you and I might have thought that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was
saying that you can't effectively make the obligation less but you will
transgress to continue to live in that marital state if it's considered
like בעילת זנות, be'ilat zenut, it doesn't have... of the full safeguards
of marriage and therefore it is more like fornication than it is
like marriage. Marriage has something that comes—the whole idea of the כתובה
kesuvah *Ketubah*, the whole idea of this מסכת masechet. *masechet* of נישואין
nissu'in, *nissuin*, of what gives it its weight, is the fact that
it has all of these reciprocal obligations and all of these protections.
So the simple sense of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* is
that you have effectively lowered the amount,
but then you transgress.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is actually going to take this one step
further and
argue that you don't even manage to succeed in lowering the amount
according to רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*. Let's take a look.
כל הפוחת *kol hapocheis* says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, אפילו בתנאי *afilu
betnai*, even if you explicitly try to stipulate that it should be
less. אלמא קסבר תנאי בטל *alma kasavar tnai batel*. So it seems
that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says that that stipulation is
void. Again, not clear, there's a long תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* now here
when this came up earlier that tries to figure out how the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* knows that. But somehow the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes
that for רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir. *Rabbi Meir*, he's not just saying
that
you are transgressing, but he's actually saying that the stipulation to make
it less is void and you haven't actually succeeded in making it
less. Maybe because it's in the כל הפוחת הממעיט *kol hapocheis hamameit*,
somebody who's attempting to be reduced the amount, but you don't actually
succeed, but even that attempt makes it be a זנות *zenut*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אלמא קסבר תנאי בטל *alma kasavar tnai
batel*, ואית ליה *ve'is lei* she still gets the full amount, you
just attempted to make it less. וכיון דאמר לה *ve'cheivan de'amar lah*
so then how is it ביאת זנות bi'as zenus. *biat zenut* if
it's still the full amount? Because since the husband said to her,
לית ליך *leis lich* you don't have 200, you only have 100,
אלא מנה *ela mane* you only have 100, לא lo, סמכה דעתה
*lo samcha daatah* so even though in principle she has 200, since
she thinks that she only has 100, that subjective sense that she
doesn't have the protections, even though it's not in true and fact,
is enough to create ביאת זנות bi'as zenus *biat zenut*. והוה לה
ביאתה ביאת זנות bi'as zenus. *v'hava lah biatah biat zenut* and that's
ביאת זנות *biat zenut*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s first big חידוש
chiddush. *chiddush*, which is questionable, not clear how it got it from
the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*, is that the תנאי *tnai* is בטל *batel*,
which isn't clear, so the woman has the full amount. And then
the second part of that is that even though she has the
full amount, it's still ביאת זנות *biat zenut* because she thinks she
doesn't. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wants to understand why is this
condition בטל *batel*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: והשמינן
ליה לרבי מאיר דאמר כל המתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה תנאי בטל
*ve'hashminan lei l'Rabbi Meir de'amar kol hamasneh al mah shekatuv baTorah tnai
batel* don't we hear, don't we know that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
*Rabbi Meir* said that if you try to stipulate against a תורה
*Torah* obligation, even a financial one, the condition is בטל *batel*. הא
בדרבנן תנאי קיים *habderabbanan tnai kayyam* and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes
that he specifically meant a biblical obligation. If you stipulate against a
rabbinic obligation, it's actually binding. So why can't you stipulate against כתובה
kesuvah *Ketubah*? Can't you stipulate for רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*
against a rabbinic monetary obligation?
You could have said רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* is reinforcing
the כתובה kesuvah *Ketubah*. It's different. He wants to protect it more
than other rabbinic obligations. That's what it sounds like, specifically because it's
about marriage and ביאת זנות *biat zenut* and so on. But the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* rather than making כתובה kesuvah, *Ketubah* unique or making
it in that way says the following: קסבר רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir,
כתובה kesuvah. דאורייתא *kasavar Rabbi Meir ketubah de'Oraisa*. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
*Rabbi Meir* may actually hold that כתובה kesuvah? *Ketubah* is biblical. We
had that debate earlier. And therefore you cannot stipulate against it. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is very מחודש *mechudash*. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir,
*Rabbi Meir*, all he seems to be saying is that you might
succeed in changing the amount, but you are transgressing by doing so,
and maybe every day you continue to live together that way you're
transgressing. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* changes רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*
to say that the attempt to change the amount does not succeed.
Why not? Because it's מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה *matneh al mah
shekatuv baTorah* and כתובה kesuvah *Ketubah* is דאורייתא *d'Oraisa*. That's also a
חידוש *chiddush*. You could have just said that maybe he protects the
כתובה kesuvah. *Ketubah* institution. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* made it specifically
כתובה kesuvah *Ketubah* is דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* and מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה
*matneh al mah shekatuv baTorah* and therefore you don't succeed. And even
though you don't succeed, it's still ביאת זנות *biat zenut* because the
woman thinks that the amount is actually less. So that's רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir. *Rabbi Meir*. Now we continue. So both רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* say to
directly try to change the amount doesn't achieve anything. רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir* says even the attempt makes it ביאת זנות *biat zenut*. To
be מוחל mochel, *mocheil* the amount for רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi
Yehuda* succeeds and is permissible. For רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* presumably that's
an interesting question: Can the woman not even be מוחל mochel, *mocheil*?
I mean, being מוחל *mocheil* is it מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה
*matneh al mah shekatuv baTorah*? Being מוחל *mocheil* is just being מוחל
*mocheil*, right? So it sounds like though from the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
that even an attempt to be מוחל *mocheil* wouldn't work for רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and it would also be ביאת זנות *biat zenut*
just in the attempt. Now we're going to get a third position.
תניא ותנא בברייתא *Tanya v'tana b'baraisa*, רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says כל
הפוחת לבתולה ממאתיים ולאלמנה ממנה הרי זו ביאת זנות *kol hapocheis l'besulah
mi'masayim u'l'almanah mi'maneh harei zu biat zenut* and that any attempt to
lower the amount is a ביאת זנות *biat zenut*. רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yosi. *Rabbi Yosi* says, now here's רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi *Rabbi Yosi*,
we haven't seen this yet, רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi *Rabbi Yosi* says
רשאי *rashai* you're allowed. So רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi *Rabbi Yosi* actually
says that you can one step further than רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
*Rabbi Yehuda*. Not only can you be מוחל *mocheil* after you start
with the base amount, but she can actually from the outset stipulate
to a lesser amount. And Rebbi Yehuda omer רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
אומר, the middle position. Rotzeh koseiv livsuloh shtar shel masayim v'hi koseves
lo hizkabalti mimcha maneh רוצה כותב לבתולה שטר של מאתים והיא כותבת
לו התקבלתי ממך מנה. Rotzeh koseiv livsuloh shtar shel masayim v'hi koseves
lo hizkabalti mimcha maneh. You can start with 200 and she can
write a receipt for 100. Ul'almanah maneh
ולאלמנה מנה, Ul'almanah maneh, or for a widow 100, v'hi koseves lo
hizkabalti mimcha chamishim והיא כותבת לו התקבלתי ממך חמשים, v'hi koseves lo
hizkabalti mimcha chamishim, and she can write a receipt for 50. So
now the Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this: u'savar Rebbi Yosi rishai
וסבר רבי יוסי רשאי? u'savar Rebbi Yosi rishai? So now we have
the third position of Rebbi Yosi רבי יוסי. Rebbi Yosi Rebbi Yehuda
רבי יהודה says you can write a receipt, but you have to
start with a base amount. Rebbi Meir רבי מאיר says you'll never
succeed in lowering the amount and you'll just make it into biznut
ביזנות. biznut. And Rebbi Yosi רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi says you can
even start with a lesser amount. U'savar Rebbi Yosi rishai וסבר רבי
יוסי רשאי? u'savar Rebbi Yosi rishai? Does Rebbi Yosi רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yosi say you're allowed to start with a lesser amount? Vermini ורמינהי,
Vermini, I'll ask you on this: ein osin kesuvos isha mitaltlin mipnei
tikkun ha-olam אין עושין כתובת אשה מטלטלין מפני תיקון העולם. ein osin
kesuvos isha mitaltlin mipnei tikkun ha-olam. We have a braisa ברייתא braisa
that says that you do not make
the kesuvah כתובה kesuvah of a woman, you don't designate
chattel, not real estate to be used to pay the kesuvah כתובה
kesuvah of a woman. Now again, as Michael has discussed and pointed
out the other day, this does not mean to take away her
liens on the real estate, that's something that we discussed, you're generally
not able to do, certainly not to make it less
than the right to have liens over 200 zuz זוז, zuz, but
the basic language of the kesuvah כתובה kesuvah, is kol hanichasai achrayin
כל הנכסי אחראין kol hanichasai achrayin
and that's a t'nai beis din תנאי בית דין. t'nai beis din.
So you're not here reducing the liens on the real estate, but
you're specifically designating chattel, mitaltlin מטלטלין, mitaltlin, to be used, the example
I gave was your Wedgwood China, you're specifically designating that to be
used to pay off the kesuvah כתובה, kesuvah not to exclude from
the liens on the real estate. Okay, so the braisa ברייתא braisa
says you don't do that. Why? Mipnei tikkun ha-olam מפני תיקון העולם.
mipnei tikkun ha-olam. What's the tikkun ha-olam תיקון העולם? tikkun ha-olam? The
tikkun ha-olam תיקון העולם tikkun ha-olam is that the chattel will be
destroyed, the Wedgwood China will break, real estate can't get stolen, but
China who knows what can happen to it? And therefore the woman
will, or it'll reduce in value, and then she'll be out,
the full amount of the kesuvah כתובה. kesuvah All right, but we'll
see, the question is maybe you should just then go to the
real estate. Okay, ein osin kesuvos isha mitaltlin mipnei tikkun ha-olam אין
עושין כתובת אשה מטלטלין מפני תיקון העולם. ein osin kesuvos isha mitaltlin
mipnei tikkun ha-olam. Amar Rebbi Yosi אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rebbi Yosi,
Rebbi Yosi רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi said, v'chi mah tikkun ha-olam yesh
bazeh וכי מה תיקון העולם יש בזה? v'chi mah tikkun ha-olam yesh
bazeh? What type of good societal function is served by this? Vehalo
ein kesuvos והלא אין כתובות, Vehalo ein kesuvos, the amount doesn't remain
fixed, u'pochsin ופוחתין, u'pochsin, and they could become worthless later on. Now
that's a little bizarre, that seems to be, no, he's talking about
chattel. So that seems to be exactly what the Tanna Kamma תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma was saying. What's bothering you? So that's what the
Gemara גמרא Gemara is going to ask. Gemara גמרא Gemara says, Tanna
Kamma nami ein osin ka-amar תנא קמא נמי אין עושין קאמר. Tanna
Kamma nami ein osin ka-amar. It sounds like he thought the Tanna
Kamma תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said you're allowed to make it, and
he was saying why should you be allowed to use chattel? The
chattel might go down in value, etc. But the Tanna Kamma תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma also said you're not allowed to make it. So
what are they disagreeing about? So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says, ella
lav hachi ka-amar אלא לאו הכי קאמר. ella lav hachi ka-amar. This
is what it must be saying. Bamah devarim amurim במה דברים אמורים,
Bamah devarim amurim, when are you not allowed to make the chattel
as the lien of the kesuvah כתובה? kesuvah Beshelo kibel alav achrayus
בשלא קיבל עליו אחריות, Beshelo kibel alav achrayus, when you don't accept
responsibility for its value, meaning that you only can collect from the
chattel itself. You're not allowed to designate the Wedgwood China and say
this is the only place you can collect the kesuvah כתובה kesuvah
from, because then what will happen? It'll break, and the woman will
be out. So you're not allowed to do it if you don't
accept responsibility for it, you don't back it up with the liens
on the real estate. Aval kibel alav achrayus אבל קיבל עליו אחריות,
Aval kibel alav achrayus, if it was backed up, you accept responsibility
that if it breaks then you will be liable and you'll pay
from the rest of your property, osin עושין, osin, you are allowed
to designate that she could collect from chattel. Ve-asa Rebbi Yosi u-rami
ואתא רבי יוסי ורמי, Ve-asa Rebbi Yosi u-rami, and Rebbi Yosi רבי
יוסי Rebbi Yosi comes along and says that's not enough. Ki kibel
alav achrayus amai osin כי קיבל עליו אחריות אמאי עושין? Ki kibel
alav achrayus amai osin? Why do you think you solved the problem
just because you accept liability for it, you the husband? Vehalo ein
kesuvos והלא אין כתובות, Vehalo ein kesuvos, the amount isn't fixed, u'pochsin
ופוחתין, u'pochsin, and it might go down in value. So even if
you accept liability for its breakage, but if it's still around, she's
limited to collect from the China. Well the China might not be
worth as much when it comes time to collect her kesuvah כתובה.
kesuvah. So Rebbi Yosi רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi says that's not good
enough, you have not fully protected the woman's interests. Okay, so that's
a debate about designating chattel, not real estate, and are you fully
protecting the woman's interests? So now let's see why the Gemara גמרא
Gemara thinks that's relevant. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this:
hashta u'mah
hasam השתא ומה התם, hashta u'mah hasam, over there by the case
of the China, dideilma pochos דדילמא פוחת, dideilma pochos, maybe it'll go
down in value, chayish Rebbi Yosi חייש רבי יוסי, chayish Rebbi Yosi,
Rebbi Yosi רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi is concerned to protect her interests
that it should never be worth less, she should never collect less
than the full amount. Hacha devadai ka-pochis הכא דודאי קא פוחת, Hacha
devadai ka-pochis, here where you're clearly making the amount less, you're stipulating
that it should be 100, not 200, lo kol shekein לא כל
שכן, lo kol shekein, how much more so should Rebbi Yosi רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi not allow this? So why did Rebbi Yosi רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi allow you to stipulate less than 200 if he's
so interested in protecting the woman's interests? The answer is obvious. The
answer is: hachi hashta הכי השתא? hachi hashta? What type of comparison
is that? Hasam lo yada detimchol התם לא ידעה דתמחול, Hasam lo
yada detimchol, there she's not aware that she should concede to it.
She wants her full 200, and you the husband are saying... Get
it from the ציינא. Tzaina. So she might be cheated out. She
is demanding her full two hundred and you're setting up a scenario
where she might not be able to collect the full two hundred.
The ציינא Tzaina might be worth less later on. Okay, so that's
one-sided, so you're not allowed to do that one-sided to compromise her
interests. But הכא, hacha, but in this case ידעה וקמחלה, yada v'kamachla,
it was an agreement. You wrote the כתובה kesuvah? initially for
a hundred, so she was a party to that. She agreed to
that stipulation. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi allows you a lesser amount
if she agrees. He just says that if she hasn't agreed, then
he's obviously going to come and protect her interests. Okay, so we
have a three-way debate. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says that if she
agrees, you can have a lesser amount. רבי יהודה says
you must start with the base amount, but then afterwards she can
waive it and effectively make it less. And רבי מאיר says you
can't even effectively make it less and even an attempt to do
so is בעילת זנות. beilat zenut. So now we're going to see
what the implications of רבי מאיר's position is and how do we
פסקן. pasken. Let's take a look.
אחותיה דרמי בר חמא, Achotei d'Rami bar Chama, so the sister of
רמי בר חמא, Rami bar Chama, הויא נסיבא לרבי אביא, havya nesiva
l'Rebbi Avya, was married to רבי אביא. Rebbi Avya. אירכס כתובתה, Irkas
kesuvtasa, her כתובה kesuvah was lost. Not getting divorced, her כתובה kesuvah.
was just lost. This happens by the way more than once. I
have been going back from a wedding, sometimes I was the מסדר,
mesader, sometimes I wasn't, and I get a call from the חתן,
choson, we can't find the כתובה, kesuvah? what do we do? Okay,
so first of all you have to write a replacement כתובה kesuvah
and the replacement כתובה kesuvah is called
כתובה דאירכסא. kesuvah d'irkasa. אירכס irkas is the Aramaic for lost, אירכס
כתובתה. irkas kesuvtasa. And the language of that כתובה kesuvah. is that
the עדים edim sign it, if you can get the original עדים
edim and they say we originally signed a כתובה kesubah. ואיכס v'irkas
and it was lost and we're testifying that this was what was
in the original כתובה. kesubah.
Wait, you write the whole thing all over again?
Pretty much. Okay, but you have to write it's even a lengthier
text because you have to sort of indicate.
And they live with each other until they have the כתובה?
kesubah, Yes, so I'm going to discuss that. Let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so the כתובה kesubah was lost, אירכס כתובתה.
irkas kesuvtasa. אתו לקמיה דרב יוסף, Atu l'kamei d'Rav Yosef, they came
before רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. אמר להו, Amar lehu, he said to
them, הכי אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, hachi amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel, this is what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the name
of שמואל, Shmuel, זו דברי רבי מאיר. zu divrei Rebbi Meir. The
idea that it's בעילת זנות beilat zenut is the position of רבי
מאיר. אבל חכמים אומרים, Aval Chachamim omrim, but the sages say, משהא
אדם עם אשתו שתים ושלש שנים בלא כתובה, masha adam im ishto
shtayim v'shalosh shanim belo kesuvah, that you can go two or three
years without writing a substitute כתובה. kesubah. What does just mean whatever,
an indefinite period of time? I mean probably not like twenty or
thirty years, eventually you've got to get around to it, but there's
no big rush. Okay, that's a way of articulating that, of expressing
that idea. Now the first point is whoever said that רבי מאיר
said that you couldn't hang around without a written
כתובה? kesubah The amount is still a hundred or two hundred, you
haven't changed the amount, you just lost a piece of paper. Remember
we taught that even without the piece of paper the obligations are
there. But the גמרא Gemara reasonably understands as Michael is saying that
if just because the woman in her mind thinks that the amount
is less, even when it's full, is enough to create בעילת זנות,
beilat zenut, so also the absence of the piece of paper of
the document is enough to create in her mind a subjective בעילת
זנות. beilat zenut. She feels if this my husband can divorce me
at any time and I'm not protected, I don't have a document.
Even if you say no no you have the protection anyway, she
doesn't feel protected, she doesn't have the document. And maybe she knows
that the debt is there, but she feels he'll just claim he
paid it. When I have a document, I have proof that he
hasn't paid. So the woman will reasonably feel not protected and therefore
for רבי מאיר it would be a בעילת זנות beilat zenut just
to not have the physical document. But the sages say that's not
a problem. Okay so now we're going to have to see how
we פסקן pasken because this is an important decision. You're the rabbi,
you get that call, do you have to tell them don't do
anything, I have to turn around and get back to you and
write you a כתובה kesubah, or fax a כתובה kesubah, for you
to sign, what do you have to do? How do we פסקן?
pasken? Like רבי מאיר or like the חכמים? Chachamim? So let's take
a look. אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said
back, והאמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי מאיר בגזירותיו, V'ha'amar Rav
Nachman amar Shmuel halacha k'Rebbi Meir bigzeirotav, but one minute, it might
be true that the sages argue on רבי מאיר, but we also
say we rule like רבי מאיר with his edicts, his גזירות. gezeirot.
אי הכי, Ei hachi, okay fine, you rule like רבי מאיר, if
that's the way you feel, זיל כתוב לה, zil katuv la, go
write her a substitute כתובה. kesubah So it sounds like we פסקן
pasken like רבי מאיר in this case. Now it is funny that
the גמרא Gemara calls this a גזירה. gezeira. Right, גזירות gezeirot are
normally like safeguards, not necessarily a safeguard that you might do a
rabbinic transgression, you might be safeguarding other types of things. But you
know the גמרא Gemara often distinguishes between גזירותיו gezeirotav and תקנותיו. takanotav.
But this is somehow seen as a גזירה gezeira in the sense
of protecting the sanctity of marriage or the proper sense of the
context of what marriage is with all of its protection. So it's
interesting that the גמרא Gemara calls this idea of labeling it בעילת
זנות beilat zenut as a type of a גזירה. gezeira. Not גזירה
gezeira again like don't read by candlelight on שבת, Shabbos, you might
tip the candle, but a גזירה gezeira to protect the institute and
the protections of marriage. Okay, so this sounds like we rule like
רבי מאיר. כי אתא רב דימי, Ki ata Rav Dimi, so we'll
see to the end and then I'll tell you what we do
למעשה. l'ma'aseh. כי אתא רב דימי Ki aso Rav Dimi when רב
דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אמר רב שמעון
בן פזי אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי משום בר קפרא, amar Rav
Shimon ben Pazi amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi mishum bar Kappara, and
actually we're about to get into a little complicated piece so let
me just pause here and tell you what we do הלכה למעשה.
halacha l'maaseh. So הלכה למעשה halacha l'maaseh we do very quickly try
to create a substitute כתובה. kesubah, By the way, it's not just
people that call you from the wedding and they misplaced it. More
than once I've had a call from a couple that's been married
20, 30 years and they can't locate their כתובה. kesubah They move,
they can't locate their כתובה, or my parents actually were once looking
at the כתובה they have hung up on the wall and realized
that the not a mistake but that the signatures had completely, you
know, whatever, disappeared, like, what, faded, so they were illegible. So you
have to write a substitute כתובה. But can you say, do you
say that you have to stop living together, sleep in separate rooms,
right, until you do it or until you do it? So in
principle that's the answer, but the רמ"א Rema actually says that nowadays
after תקנת רבינו גרשום takanas Rabbeinu Gershom that a man cannot divorce
his wife, a husband cannot divorce his wife against her will, so
you don't it's not the problem of ביאת זנות. The problem of
ביאת זנות is she feels that even as they're having sex, it's
not really in, you know, with the sort of protections of marriage
because maybe he's just using me and he's going to divorce me
tomorrow morning, and you know, and so she has to feel protected.
So the כתובה protects her against easy divorce. So the basic idea
of the protection is she knows he's not just going to callously
divorce her. So the רמ"א Rema says, it's interesting that he sort
of focuses it on that way, that now that a woman can't
be divorced against her will, even without the כתובה, written כתובה, she
knows that she's protected in that way, so it's not a ביאת
זנות. Nevertheless, we try to take care of it as soon as
possible, but we don't tell them stop living together, you know, until
I get
it taken care of. Good question. I mean, most ספרדים Sefardim nowadays
have one way or another adopted תקנת רבינו גרשום, takanas Rabbeinu Gershom,
but it's an interesting question about how ספרדים Sefardim deal with that.
Yeah, I don't know the full answer to that.
And you said you have to write a new one if even
some signatures or you can't use the same one even if signatures
are faded? You have to write a new one.
No, because you have to write no, no, because it's not giving
honest well, no, because the witnesses testify there's a whole problem about
writing two כתובות kesubos because maybe you give even if you have
the same witnesses, why not just rewrite it? Why do you have
to use a different נוסח nusach if you have the same witnesses?
If you had different
witnesses you understand why, because other witnesses hadn't witnessed the original event,
but if it's the same witnesses, the reason you can't is because
maybe the woman is just saying that she lost the כתובה and
now she's going to have two כתובות kesubos and she's going to
use it twice.
Alright, how do you know though? Maybe she managed to create a
facsimile, you know, the whole problem. Anyway, you don't write the identical
one because then you're afraid that there are two
documents, equivalent documents on the same date.
Because the different נוסח nusach says that the original one was lost,
so therefore because
there were two different courts or something.
That's true, I guess if it's that way once he pays oh,
and if you're saying once he pays he's handed over the first
כתובה, then it doesn't matter whether same נוסח nusach or different נוסח.
nusach.
That's true, I guess if it's that way...
yeah, I'm not sure, I'm not sure. I have to figure that
out.
Right. Alright, alright, alright. I hear the question. Let's go on. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, כי אתא רב
דימי, Ki aso Rav Dimi, now we're going to have a question
about what was the scope of this debate of רבי יוסי who
says that you can lower and the others who say you cannot
lower the amount, at least initially. כי אתא רב דימי אמר רב
שמעון בן פזי, Ki aso Rav Dimi amar Rav Shimon ben Pazi,
when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael said
in the name of רב שמעון בן פזי, Rav Shimon ben Pazi,
אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי משום בר קפרא amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi mishum bar Kappara in the name of רבי יהושע בן לוי
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi in the name of בר קפרא, bar Kappara,
says the following. מחלוקת בתחילה. Machlokes betchila. The debate of רבי יוסי
that says you can change
the amount and רבי מאיר and
רבי יהודה say
you can't, at least initially, is only at the beginning
of
the wedding. אבל
בסוף, Aval besof, at the end, דברי הכל אינה מוחלת, divrei hakol
eina mochelas, even רבי יוסי says you can't change the amount. Now
the question is going to be what the end means, but for
now let's just say after they've had sex, so then the obligations
kick in. So then רבי יוסי would say you can't change the
amount. I mean, he could be מוחל, but to change the base
amount, the initial base amount, you have to do it before the
obligation begins, right? Once the obligation begins, then he's obligated. Then she
could be מוחלת, mocheles, but the obligation has been defined once they
actually, you know, have had sex. Okay, so אינה מוחלת. eina mochelas.
רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, בין
בזו ובין בזו מחלוקת. bein b'zo u'vein b'zo machlokes. No, they debate
both cases. אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abbahu, now we're going to
try to clarify what beginning and end mean. לדידי מיפרשא לי מיניה
דרבי יוחנן, L'didi mefarsha li minei d'Rabbi Yochanan, it was explained to
me the position of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan in the name of
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, excuse me, דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, d'amar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, I and רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi, the first opinion, לא פליגינא, lo palginan, we don't debate.
מה בתחילה דקאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Mai betchila d'ka'amar Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi, when רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi says
that the debate is at the outset, that means תחלת חופה, techillas
chuppah, at the, that means the beginning of the חופה, chuppah, that
they don't debate that before the, you know, I'm sorry, that that's
when they debate, before the, you know, before the חופה. chuppah. ומאי
סוף, U-mai sof, and at the end when everybody agrees you can't
change it is סוף ביאה, sof biah, is when they've actually had
sex. וכי קאמינא אנא בין בזו ובין בזו מחלוקת, V'chi ka-amina ana
bein b'zo u-vein b'zo machlokes, and when I say that they debate
both cases, beginning and end, I mean a different beginning and end.
I mean תחלת חופה, techillas chuppah, the before the חופה, chuppah, וסוף
חופה, v'sof chuppah, or at the חופה chuppah but before sex, והיא
תחלת ביאה. v'hi techillas biah. Okay, which is the beginning of sex.
So basically, this is going to get confusing, okay, but basically we're
identifying three places, okay? There's חופה, chuppah,
there's ביאה, biah, okay, and there's ביאה, biah, right? And now this
partly goes to the whole question, right, about when do the כתובה
obligations begin? If you remember the other day we had the question
like when the תוספת tosefes begins. Does the תוספת tosefes begin at
חופה? chuppah? Does the תוספת tosefes begin at ביאה? biah? So in
a related way the question is when has the obligations begun that
it's too late to change the amount? Because once the obligation began,
you can always be מוחל, but to fundamentally change the amount, okay?
So the first position of רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi, right, רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, this is
the way the גמרא Gemara is going to sort of say it
says they argue at תחלה, techilla, okay? So תחלה, techilla, here, this
is what's going to be called before is going to be called
תחלת חופה, techillas chuppah, yeah, right. This really means before, okay? So
רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi is going to say,
I'm sorry,
רבי
יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, okay, and this is רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. The
reason I'm making a whole chart is because we're going to have
more than one version of this. Okay, it's רבי יהושע בן לוי
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi says here is מחלוקת, machlokes, they argue at
תחלה, techilla, and here everybody agrees, you know,
you know, everybody says can't change, everybody
says cannot, cannot change. Okay, that's what he says. רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says they argue in both cases, but what he, but what
how now the way it's being explained, they argue in both cases
תחלה וסוף techilla v'sof means תחלת חופה techillas chuppah before the חופה
chuppah and סוף חופה sof chuppah means at the חופה chuppah and
therefore really רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi and רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan really agree. That the מחלוקת machlokes is through the
חופה, chuppah, can you change the amount? And everybody agrees when you
get to the ביאה biah you can't change the amount. So that's
that version.
Okay, we're not, we don't know what רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi would say about חופה chuppah though, right?
No, because we're saying that they all agree.
No, you know, that he didn't say it.
He didn't say it, we're making them all agree. Okay, so גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay. כי אתא רבין אמר, Ki ata Ravin
amar,
now when רבין Ravin came, he had a different version of the
positions of of this debate. He said, כי אתא רבין אמר רבי
שמעון בן פזי אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי משום בר קפרא, ki
ata Ravin amar Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
mishum Bar Kappara, that the רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi position was the following. מחלוקת לבסוף. Machlokes l'vsof.
They argue at the end. אבל בתחילה, Aval b'techilla, at the outset,
דברי הכל מוחלת, divrei hakol mocheles, even everybody, even רבי יהודה says
you can change the amount if you do it at the beginning.
Okay, ורבי יוחנן אמר V'Rabbi Yochanan amar בין בזו ובין בזו מחלוקת.
bein b'zo u-vein b'zo machlokes.
No, they argue beginning and end. So this is like the mirror
image. They argue at the end, they agree at the beginning that
it's possible. And now we're going to make the two say the
same thing. אמר רבי אבהו לדידי מפרשא לי מיניה דרבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabbi Abahu lididi mifarsha li mineih d'Rabbi Yochanan, it was explained to
me in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan דאנא ורבי יהושע
בן לוי לא פליגינן אהדדי, d'ana v'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi lo palginan
ahadadi, we don't argue with one another. מאי לבסוף דאמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי, Mai l'vsof d'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi,
when רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi says that at
the end that's where they debate, that means סוף חופה, sof chuppah,
meaning, meaning after the חופה chuppah before the sex. ומאי תחילה U-mai
techilla where's the תחילה techilla that it's everybody says it's okay? תחלת
חופה, Techillas chuppah, the beginning of the חופה, chuppah, before the חופה.
chuppah. וכי קאמינא אנא V'chi ka-amina ana and when I, רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, say, I'm going to put it on the board, בין
בזו ובין בזו מחלוקת, bein b'zo u-vein b'zo machlokes, they debate both
cases, תחלת ביאה וסוף ביאה techillas biah v'sof biah
meaning it's the beginning of the ביאה biah meaning the, the חופה
chuppah after the חופה chuppah and the after the sex. So basically
this version
has
them say the mirror image, okay, I need another color. What happened?
You get a whole bunch of them. I had all of them
but I put them away.
Break it open, the new pack. Make it bigger
though.
Okay. So this says they argue at the beginning, not at the
end. The other version says that everybody says that at the
beginning everyone says can change,
okay, and at the end is the מחלוקת, machlokes, okay, and רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan in this version says בין... bein... בין בזו בין
בזו מחלוקת bein bizo bein bizo machlokes
means
these two. So they're not really arguing, okay? According to this, you
see how we manage to make a third case so we shift
it so that they can agree. So according to this, everybody agrees
before the חופה chuppah it can change and everybody disagrees after, you
know, after the חופה, chuppah, after the ביאה. biah. And that's how
we made them the same. According to the first version, the green
version, it's the opposite. Everybody agrees after the ביאה biah it can't
change and the מחלוקת machlokes is in all the stages before the
ביאה. biah. Okay? So two different versions of it, but in both
cases having רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi say the same thing. Now the גמרא Gemara ends
this thing and the following. אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Pappa says
רב פפא Rav Pappa אילאו דאמרי רב אבוהו Ilov d'amri Rav Avahu
had רב אבוהו Rav Avahu not said רב דימי מפרש לי מיניה
דרבי יוחנן Rav Dimi mifarshei minei d'Rabbi Yochanan דאנא ורבי יהושע בן
לוי לא פליגינן אהדדי d'ana u'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi lo pliginan ahadadi
if we had not had this statement of רב פפא Rav Pappa
in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to say that רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
were really saying the same thing, so הוה אמינא רבי יוחנן ורבי
יהושע בן לוי פליגי hava amina Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
pligi I would have said no, I would have said רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi are
disagreeing, are really disagreeing as to the debates of the תנאים Tannaim
here, they're not saying the same things, but רב דימי ורבין
לא פליגי Rav Dimi v'Ravin lo pligi but the two versions of
the רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan debate those
don't really argue. Why? מאי סוף דקאמר רבין סוף חופה ומאי תחילה
דקאמר רב דימי תחילת ביאה. Mai sof d'ka amar Ravin sof chuppah
u'mai t'chilla d'ka amar Rav Dimi t'chillat biah. Okay, and I
don't know if I want to try to make this work out,
but what I would have said is rather than this which has
basically רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua and רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan agreeing, it's saying it in different ways, but the מחלוקת
machlokes is what רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said and what רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said, the green version or the red version, there's another
way to do it, I don't think it's worth doing it on
the board but you'll trust me, there's another way to do it
that takes רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi at face value and has them actually arguing but
has the two versions of רב דימי ורבין Rav Dimi v'Ravin to
effectively mean the same things just using different languages for saying the
same thing. Okay, and he says I would have rather, if we're
going to reduce the debate, I would have rather reduced the debate
between רבין ורב דימי Ravin v'Rav Dimi rather than have collapsed the
debate of רבי יהושע בן לוי ורבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
v'Rabbi Yochanan. So the גמרא Gemara says why? What difference does it
make once we're trying to collapse one of the debates? So the
גמרא Gemara says מאי קמשמע לן? mai kamashma lan? What are you
teaching me? הא קמשמע לן דפליגי תרי אמוראי טעמא דנפשייהו ולא פליגי
תרי אמוראי אליבא דחד אמורא. Ha kamashma lan d'pligi trei amorai ta'ama
d'nafshaihu v'lo pligi trei amorai aliba d'chad amora.
It would be better to say that the two אמוראים Amoraim are
disagreeing based on logic than that they're disagreeing on what an אמורא
Amora said. Meaning, רבי יהושע בן לוי ורבי יוחנן Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi u'Rabbi Yochanan if they're really arguing, if they're not saying the
same thing, what they're arguing is what area does it make sense
to say the מחלוקת machlokes occurred between רבי יהודה ורבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yehuda v'Rabbi Yossi, right? So they're arguing about a סברא. sevara. So
it's better to say that they're arguing about a סברא sevara and
they're arguing against one another than to say that there's a debate
about what רבי יוחנן ורבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi actually said. What difference does it make? Because as רש"י
Rashi says and תוספות tosfos says more succinctly, he says we always
argue for סברא. sevara. That's what the whole ש"ס Shas is, I
think this way you think that way. So רבי יהושע בן לוי
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi thinks that the debate makes more sense in
this realm and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan thinks the debate makes more
sense in that realm, that's fine. But to say that there's a
debate about what they originally said means that there's actually a problem
in transmission, right? That there's a different version, that רבין Ravin had
one version of what they said and whoever was the other one
רב דימי Rav Dimi had a different version. So that actually means
that somebody got it wrong, got the transmission wrong. So he says
I would have rather said that they're arguing and they're arguing in
the סברא sevara of where you know what makes sense that the
מחלוקת machlokes occurred and said that rather than saying that there was
a debate about the right version of what the two of them
said. We do have that too but if I had to choose
I'd rather be a debate in סברא. sevara. Fine. Alright, that's the
end of that. Let's not belabor that point anymore. Next משנה. mishnah
And now we're
okay, see if we can catch up. נותנין לבתולה שנים עשר חודש
משתבעה הבעל לפרנס את עצמה. Notnin l'betulah shneim asar chodesh mishetava'ah habaal
l'farnes et atzmah.
So from the time that the husband says, right everybody thinks that
oh twelve months after קידושין kiddushin they got married. No. Twelve months
after קידושין kiddushin then she might have got married at the age
of two or the age of the old age of five, okay,
it was only many years later the husband said now it's time
for us to start living together, okay? So from the moment that
he says I think we have to move from קידושין kiddushin to
נשואין, nisuin,
from that point on she's got twelve months to get her what
do you call it? Trousseau together
and to say fine I'm ready to get married but you gotta
give me twelve months, okay? So she's got twelve months to take
care of getting ready. Presumably that assumes that he'd like to get
married tomorrow but she's entitled to twelve months from the time he
says. Okay, so they're already קידושין, kiddushin, and now he's saying I
want to move on to נישואין, nissu'in, and we give her twelve
months to get her stuff together. וכשם שנותנין לאשה כך נותנין לאיש,
U'keshem shenotnin l'ishah kach notnin l'ish,
but similarly, you know, he can say I want to take twelve
months to get the house ready and to get the, you know,
and to get everything prepared for us to get married. Of course
the question is then why was he the one, then why was
he the one saying let's get married? Maybe she was the one
saying, it's a little hard to understand the scenario because it seems
like just the implicit social contract here is that he's the one
that gets to say when it's time. But anyway, maybe the bride's
father is pushing him or something. In whatever the scenario is, he's
entitled to twelve months as well if he needs it לפרנס את
עצמו. l'farnos et atzmo. ואלמנה שלושים יום, V'almanah shloshim yom, that's a
first marriage, but if however it's a second marriage, so then it's
assumed that she's more independent and therefore she's more she doesn't need
as much time, you know, to get her trousseau together. And maybe
also they wouldn't make as much of a bigger deal of it.
הגיע זמן ולא נישאו. Higi'a zman v'lo nisu. Now the twelve months
are up and they're not yet married. And remember this was brought
in in the very first דף daf of the מסכת. masechet There's
a whole question of who's to blame. The משנה mishnah doesn't discuss
who's to blame, but it just says the following: they're not married.
אוכלת משלו, Ochelet mishelo, then he has to start now paying the
food bills, right? Once there's נישואין, nissu'in, he has a חיוב chiyuv
of מזונות. mezonot. He has a חיוב chiyuv to support her. So
if they should be married by now and they're not, and the
beginning of the מסכת discusses does it matter who's to blame or
not, but now he starts she starts now, you know, she eats
from his, you know, on his account. He basically has to pay
for her food starting now, for her expenses. אוכלת משלו. Ochelet mishelo.
ואוכלת בתרומה. V'ochelet b'terumah. If he's a כהן, kohen, he can feed
her תרומה, terumah, okay, because תרומה terumah is cheaper. Okay, which basically
shows that a woman, a wife of a כהן kohen is entitled
to eat from תרומה terumah even before the נישואין, nissu'in, even at
the אירוסין. erusin. So it's telling you two things. Number one, from
laws of תרומה, terumah, even though she's not yet נשואה, nesu'ah, she's
only ארוסה arusah to a כהן, kohen, she's allowed to eat it.
And number two, in terms of his obligation to feed her, he
can satisfy that by feeding her תרומה, terumah, by giving her תרומה.
terumah.
רבי טרפון אומר נותנין לה הכל תרומה. Rabbi Tarfon omer notnin lah
hakol terumah. He can give the whole amount in תרומה. terumah. ורבי
עקיבא אומר מחצה חולין ומחצה תרומה. V'Rabbi Akiva omer mechtzah chullin u'mechtzah
terumah. No, half has to be חולין. chullin. Why? Because half the
month, not really half, but only once you get חומרא דרבי זירא,
Chumra d'Rabbi Zeira, but anyway a good part of the month she's
טמאה, tme'ah, she's a נידה. niddah. And when she's a נידה niddah
she can't eat תרומה. terumah. So it's not fair to give her
תרומה terumah that she'll have to sell and then get in exchange
less חולין. chullin. He has to provide her at least half of
the amount חולין, chullin, stuff that she can eat even when she's
טמאה. tme'ah. היבם אינו מאכיל בתרומה. Hayavam eino ma'achil b'terumah.
Let's say a כהן kohen was married to a woman, כהן kohen
died, and now his brother the כהן kohen is the brother-in-law has
to do יבום. yibbum. He hasn't done יבום yibbum yet, he's waiting
for יבום yibbum to be done, she's שומרת יבם. shomeret yavam. So
in that case she cannot eat תרומה, terumah, okay, even if and
we don't like say there's like a twelve-month clock and afterwards she's
able to eat תרומה. terumah. So even though it's somewhat analogous, she's
waiting to get married to this יבם, yavam, nevertheless there's no תביעה
להינשא tvi'ah l'hinasseh situation, you might think it's even more, there's a
מצוה mitzvah to do it, but no, she's not entitled to eat
תרומה. terumah. עשתה שישה חודשים בפני הבעל ושישה חודשים בפני היבם. As'tah
shishah chodashim bifnei haba'al v'shishah chodashim bifnei hayavam.
Let's say the husband, the כהן kohen husband was אירוסין, erusin, and
he said let's get married, and it was six months, and then
he dropped dead. And now it's six months that she's waiting for
יבום. yibbum. ואפילו כולן בפני הבעל, V'afilu kulan bifnei haba'al, or it
was one day before the נישואין, nissu'in and her and the כהן
kohen she was מקודשת mekudeshet to, one day before the נישואין nissu'in,
after the eleven months and twenty-nine days dropped dead on her. חסר
יום אחד בפני היבם, Chaser yom echad bifnei hayavam, and then that
last day was obviously waiting for the guy to do יבום. yibbum.
או כולן בפני היבם חסר יום אחד בפני הבעל, O kulan bifnei
hayavam chaser yom echad bifnei haba'al, that's obviously this is pretty self-apparent,
or she waited one day after the קידושין kiddushin to this guy
and he dropped dead, and now it's eleven months and twenty-nine days
in front of the יבם. yavam. In all those cases אינה אוכלת
בתרומה, einah ochelet b'terumah, she does not eat תרומה. terumah. Now רש"י
Rashi says that that last case is obvious because the משנה Mishna.
made it sound like she could wait five years for יבום yibbum
and not eat תרומה. terumah. Okay, we'll get
tomorrow's דף daf will discuss what תוספות'ס Tosafot's position on this is.
רש"י Rashi said that last case was a little bit of a
throw-in because even if you wait five years in front of the
יבם yavam she doesn't eat תרומה, terumah, she only eats תרומה terumah
in the case of a normal נישואין, Nissu'in not in the case
of a waiting יבום. yibbum. All right?
And she needs it, right,
when she does get married she will.
And she's a בת כהן bat kohen and no kids,
she's able to go back to her parents. Exactly. זו משנה ראשונה.
Zu mishnah rishonah. That was the first teaching. בית דין של אחריהן
אמרו. Beit din shel achareihen amru. Now the later בית דין beit
din said. Now by the way משנה ראשונה... mishnah rishonah... does literally
mean משנה Mishna *Mishnah* as a text. There is, I mean, there's
a whole literature about משנה Mishna ראשונה *Mishnah Rishonah*. Basically there was
early collections of משניות *Mishnayot* and even when rulings changed later, those
early collections were not rejected. So this preserves this original text of
the original משנה *Mishnah*. Again, text doesn't mean a written text, it
was oral, but the original text of the original משנה *Mishnah* was
this. And here now, but here's an update. Okay, after that, it
was revised in the following way. And it's interesting that we don't
just discard that original text. Why quote it? Why not just tell
me the הלכה *Halacha*? Phrase גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has is משנה ראשונה
לא זזה ממקומה *Mishnah Rishonah lo zazah mimmekomah*, which is basically we
preserve our earlier texts. Okay, so that was the way it was.
Here, however, is the update. The update is: בית דין שלאחריהן אמרו
*Beit Din she'achareihem amru*, אין האשה אוכלת בתרומה עד שתכנס לחופה *ein
ha'ishah ochelet bitrumah ad shetikanes lachuppah*. No, that as we'll see, for
various reasons, we don't want a woman—while yet his obligation to feed
her begins after twelve months, we don't want her to start eating
תרומה *Terumah* until חופה *Chuppah*, which by the way is to her
benefit, which means that he—he has to pay a higher food bill,
he has to feed her all חולין *Chullin*, he can't feed her
תרומה *Terumah*.
Plus, we don't want her giving תרומה *Terumah* to her family.
Right, that's going to be the reason. Let's take a look at
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
Could you give an example that she's a בת כהן *Bat Kohen*?
Yeah. He's still—the future husband, יבם *Yavam*, cannot give her תרומה *Terumah*,
even when she sits at home?
That's a good point. We'll see about that. I think that's going
to come up. Okay, so I'm going to hold off on that,
answering that. That's a good question. מנני מילי *Minani mili*? Where is
this from? That a woman has twelve months from—you know, to say—to
not be rushed into נישואין Nissu'in *Nisuin*. So אמר רב חסדא דאמר
קרא *Amar Rav Chisda d'amar kra*, the verse says: ויאמר אחיה ואמה
תשב הנערה אתנו ימים או עשור *Vayomer achiha v'imah teshev hana'arah itanu
yamim o asor*. So this is by, right, רבקה *Rivkah*, her mother
and brother said, let her stay with us for days or ten.
מאי ימים *Mai yamim*? What do days mean? אילימא תרי יומי *Ileima
terei yomei*? If it's two days, נשתעי אינשי הכי *nish'te'i inshi hachi*,
do people talk this way? אמרו ליה תרי יומי *Amru lei terei
yomei*, give us two days. אמרו להו לא *Amru lehu lo*, no.
אמרו ליה *Amru lei*, so then they'll say to them, okay, עשרה
יומי *asarah yomei*, give us ten days. Give us two days or
ten days, right? You normally—you don't bargain up, you tend to bargain
down. So, אלא מאי ימים *ella mai yamim*? שנה *Shana*. When it
says give us days, it means give us a year. And if
not a year, give us ten months. Okay, so דכתיב ימים תהיה
גאולתו *dikhtiv yamim tihyeh ge'ulato*, in a full year you can—you can
redeem by the house of, by the case of, selling the house
in a walled city. ואימא חודש *V'eima chodesh*? Maybe ימים *yamim* means
a month? And maybe it means a month or ten days, not
a year or ten months. דכתיב עד חודש ימים *Dikhtiv ad chodesh
yamim*, a month of days. So אמרי *amri* no, דנים ימים סתם
מימים סתם *danim yamim stam miyamim stam*. Take ימים *yamim* when it
comes unqualified from where it says ימים *yamim* unqualified. ואין דנים ימים
סתם מימים שנאמר בהן חודש *V'ein danim yamim stam miyamim shene'emar bahen
chodesh*, and you don't learn from a case where it says חודש
ימים *chodesh yamim* where חודש *chodesh* qualifies it. But ימים *yamim* by
itself would mean a year. So you see that they had a
right to ask for a year. And then the עבד *eved* just
says, don't hold me back. So he pressured them, but at least
in principle, we get an idea that they have the right to
hold back for a year. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this: Now, אמר רבי זירא *Amar Rabi Zeira*, תנא *tana*,
we תנא *tana* ברייתא *beraisa*: קטנה Ketannah, בין היא ובין אביה יכולים
לעכב bein hi uvein aviha yecholim le'akeiv. *Ketannah bein hi uven aviha
yecholim l'akev*. While she's still a קטנה Ketannah, *ketannah*, either she or
the father can say, I don't want to get married, I'm still
a קטנה Ketannah *ketannah*. Okay, so it's too soon. Not for—not for
a year. No, as long as she's a קטנה Ketannah *ketannah*. Okay,
so this is a new idea, that the whole idea of a
year is when she's no longer a קטנה Ketannah. *ketannah*, but once
she's a קטנה Ketannah.
*ketannah*—or when she agreed.
Well, right. But the idea that it's a year—as long as she's
a קטנה Ketannah. *ketannah*, she can basically hold back.
Now by the—okay, by the way, the question here is, what do
you mean יכולים לעכב *yecholim l'akev*? Like are you going to take
a woman kicking and screaming—screaming
into the כתובה *kesu*—into the חופה *chuppah*? Like let's say, you know,
let's say—let's say it's more than a year. You say, okay, you're
only allowed to postpone a year. Let's say she postpones more than
a year. So what—what are you going to do to her? You
know? What does that mean? So it could mean that more than
a year he doesn't have to—if you go more than the allowed
amount, he doesn't have to start feeding. But fine. But what's an
option to me? Tell me I've got five years, he doesn't have
to feed me during the five years. Tell me I've got one
year and I refuse, he also doesn't feed me during the period
where I'm refusing to go to the חופה *chuppah*. What difference does
it make, do you understand the question I'm asking?
What difference
does it make to say she has a right to postpone? She
has a right to wait. Let's say she didn't have a right
to wait. What—what are you going to say? You're—you're not going to
force her into the חופה *chuppah* against her will. What are you
going to do to her if you say you don't have a
right to wait? I don't—right to wait, I'm still refusing to go.
Yeah, but suppose a girl is a slave? What?
Well, but—but now we're going to say that—but it's not talking about
a קטנה Ketannah. *ketannah*, we're talking about a נערה na'arah. *naarah*. Anyway,
the point תוספות tosfos. *Tosafos* says to be is that if you
would say she didn't have a right, then it's sort of anticipating
what we're going to get to in the later, sort of, you
know, גמרות *Gemaras*, which is about when a woman isn't living up
to her marital obligations, that you start like reducing the amount of
her כתובה *kesuvah*. You start fining her, you know, in order—in order
to get compliance. So, but the assumption is, if you didn't say
she had a right for a year, or let's say actually the
year's up and she... But still refuses there might be some financial
penalties that we actually impose in order to get compliance, okay? We
might lower the amount of the כתובה. But is it interesting wondering
what does this mean you have the right to do it. What
would be the alternative? All right, so now the גמרא Gemara is
saying that as long as she's a קטנה, Ketannah. even more than
a year, she and her father have a right to postpone.
Meaning they agreed to get married and now
they agreed to get married when she was three. And the guy
when she was seven said okay let's actually they had קידושין Kiddushin
at three. At seven the guy said let's start living together. And
she and the father had a radical idea and said you know
what it might be better to wait till she's בת מצווה. Bas
Mitzvah. Okay, they're entitled to push it off that much.
Okay, בין היא ובין אביה יכולים לעכב.
So the
גמרא Gemara says בשלמא היא מצי מעכבא, bishlama hi matzi me'akeva, she
can postpone it, we understand,
because you know that's a חידוש. אלא אביה, ella aviha, but by
the father, אי היא ניחא לה, ei hi nicha lah, if she
wants to do נישואין Nissu'in and there's already been קידושין, Kiddushin, אביה
מאי נפקא ליה מינה? aviha mai nafka lei minnah? Right,
what's the father's right to postpone it? Meaning if she says I'm
not ready yet for marriage and I'm a קטנה, Ketannah. we understand
that that's a legitimate claim. But if the father says I'm not
ready to have her yet married, why should that be a legitimate
claim? So the גמרא Gemara says what are you talking about? The
father the father get well let's take a look. Well exactly what
the גמרא Gemara is going to say. It's actually interesting the גמרא
Gemara could have said because as long as there's no נישואין Nissu'in.
he's entitled to her מעשה ידיים ma'aseh yadayim and all those other
things. But let's see what the גמרא Gemara does say. סבר, sevar,
because the father feels, השתא לא ידעה, hashta lo yade'ah, she doesn't
know. She's seven years old. She thinks she's ready. So he thinks
she's okay.
למחר מימרדא, lemachar mimreda, you know after she gets married she'll be
too young and then she'll say she doesn't want to stay with
this guy and
מימרדא mimreda and
she'll you know rebel reject him. ונפקא, venafkah, and then he'll divorce
her because and אתיא ונפלה עלויה, asya venafala alavei, and then she's
going to be my responsibility. Okay, now this is a I got
to tell you a funny גמרא Gemara because it's more obvious the
reason he could say I don't want to have her you know
go ahead in נישואין Nissu'in, is because as long as she remains
at home, I'm entitled to her like מעשה ידיים, ma'aseh yadayim, right,
before נישואין. Nissu'in But maybe the גמרא said that's not legitimate. The
guy did קידושין, Kiddushin, he's ready to get married, why do you
have a right to stand in the way? So it needed to
find a reason within the marriage itself that he had a legitimate
claim. And yeah he's not in loco parentis, he is parentis, you
know. So he says I actually think this is a bad idea
and you should trust my judgment at this stage. But the other
interesting thing is that after נישואין, Nissu'in technically she won't be his
responsibility. If she's divorced after נישואין Nissu'in she's not his responsibility. So
even saying but I guess again from the social realities I'll be
expected to deal with her and it's just going to be it's
going to be difficult. So either she or the father while she's
still a קטנה Ketannah, can say it's not yet the right time.
Okay.
אמר רבי אבא בר לוי, amar Rabbi Abba bar Levi, אין פוסקין
על הקטנה להשיאה כשהיא קטנה. ein poskin al haketannah lehasi'ah keshihi ketannah.
You do not make a deal with the husband for a you
know for a קטנה ketana. to marry her off while she's still
a קטנה. ketana Okay, we just saw that. אבל, aval, this is
not doing קידושין, Kiddushin, this is about to marry her off, the
נישואין Nissu'in. which we just said, you know, that she or the
father can be מעכב. me'akeiv. So once you say she or the
father can be מעכב, me'akeiv, the גמרא is pretty much signaling that
the גמרא doesn't think it's a good idea for a woman to
do נישואין Nissu'in while she's a קטנה. ketana. By the way, this
is worth noting. I don't know how much better this makes it,
but you know, people are rightly scandalized when you talk about קידושי
קטנה. Kiddushei Ketannah. Here he is, she's what, she's five years old
and she she's married to this guy? So קידושין Kiddushin is only
like on paper, you know, I mean it's not they haven't really
started living together in a sexual having a life sexual life. That
begins at נישואין. Nissu'in And this גמרא is basically saying we don't
want that to happen while she's a קטנה. ketana, So okay, once
she's בת מצווה, Bas Mitzvah, fine. I mean again, not that that's
so much better, but at least then at least she's mature. I
mean there are you know people girls do have whatever you know
it does happen. Girls have sex by you know the age of
12 and 13 and so on, not that it's a good thing.
Okay, but at least the גמרא is saying here we don't want
the נישואין Nissu'in. to take place. So first it starts by saying
she or the father can can stop it, which is obviously indicating
that the גמרא thinks it's a good idea to stop it at
that you know to not have it happen. Then the גמרא goes
one step further and is black and white and says you should
not do this. Not just you have the right to stop it
but you should not marry your daughter off, do the נישואין Nissu'in
while
she is a קטנה. ketana Okay. Even when father sells his daughter
as a
slave as a קטנה.
ketana. Yeah, sells her as a slave, yeah.
Oh, it's just as a slave.
Or marries her as a קטנה. ketana, Which one? He can marry
her as a קטנה, ketana. but that's קידושין, Kiddushin, but she doesn't
start living with the guy yet, that's נישואין.
nisuin And and so if he did so it would be after
נישואין nisuin would not happen until she's what a בוגרת? bogeres?
Yeah, or a נערה. nara Now it could happen, it's legally still
allowed, but the גמרא is now is now trying to prevent it.
First it... saying the father and the daughter have the right to
say no, and now it's even saying you should say no, you
shouldn't do it.
Okay, אין פוסקין על הקטנה להשיאה כשהיא קטנה. Ein poskin al haketana
lehasia keshehi ketana. You do not arrange for a make an arrangement
to marry the girl off, do the נישואין nisuin while she's still
a קטנה. ketana, אבל פוסקין על הקטנה להשיא כשהיא גדולה, aval poskin
al haketana lehasia keshehi gedola, but you can make an arrangement, presumably
the father, while she's a קטנה ketana to get, you know, that
the נישואין nisuin will happen once she becomes an adult, like once
she's a נערה naara, after Bat Mitzvah. To the Sunday Bat Mitzvah,
Monday wedding. Okay, פשיטא pshita the גמרא says obviously. No, מהו דתימא
ליחוש דילמא מילא פחדא מהשתא וחלשא, mahu d'teima lichosh dilma mailai pachta
mehashta vechalsha, obviously you can agree, the second part, obviously you can
arrange for the נישואין nisuin, after she's a קטנה. ketana. גמרא says
no, maybe you shouldn't even arrange for it now while she's a
קטנה, even though the date is set for later. Because now she's
a קטנה and you're telling her, "hey honey, in a year after
your Bat Mitzvah you're going to get married to this guy." So
she's now very afraid, she's still 11 years old or 10 years
old. So to be even planning it might not be a good
idea. So the גמרא says דילמא מילא פחדא מהשתא וחלשא. dilma mailai
pachta mehashta vechalsha. Now she has fear and she grows, like you
know, despondent or, you know, despairing. קמשמע לן kamashma lan that we're
not concerned about that. Okay, but now we've introduced the idea that
you do not, it's you're entitled to stop to to object to
נישואין nisuin during that and actually you should object to נישואין, nisuin.
you should not do נישואין nisuin while she is a קטנה. Okay,
now the גמרא continues.
אמר רב הונא בגרה יום אחד ונתקדשה נותנין לה שלשים יום כאלמנה.
Amar Rav Huna bogra yom echad veniskadsha nosin la shloshim yom k'almana.
That once the woman hits בגרות, bagrus, 12 and a half, and
there has been קידושין, kiddushin, then she does not have 12 more
months anymore. Then if if there's been קידושין kiddushin and she hits
בגרות, bagrus, like now she's the old age of 12 and a
half, that's when you're expected to get married, then you only have
30 days. So the גמרא says מיתיבי, meisivei, I'll ask you on
this, בגרה הרי היא כתבעוה. bogra harei hi k'tvauha. Once a woman
hits בגרות, bagrus, it's like the husband said it's time to get
married. Now once he says it's time to get married, you have
12 months. מאי לאו mai lav does that not mean כתבעוה דבתולה,
k'tvauha d'besula, like when a case of a virgin and there was
and he said it's time to get married that there's 12 months?
So once she hits בגרות, bagrus, it's also 12 months, even if
he didn't demand it. לא, no, כתבעוה דאלמנה. k'tvauha d'almana. It's like
when he demands it from an אלמנה almana where it's 30 days,
okay? So it certainly doesn't sound, the גמרא is going to reject
this. תא שמע, ta shma, come and hear. בוגרת ששהתה שנים עשר
חודש. bogeret sheshahasa shneim asar chodesh. A woman hit בגרות, bagrus, 12
and a half, and now it's been 12 months, and it sounds
like the husband did not demand the wedding, it's just been 12
months since בגרות. bagrus. רבי אליעזר אומר הואיל וחייב בעלה במזונותיה יפר.
Rabbi Eliezer omer ho'il vechayav ba'ala bimzonoseiha yafer. Since the husband is
now obligated to feed her because the 12 months are up,
יפר, yafer, he can annul her vows. So anyway, we're not interested
in the vows. What we are interested in, 12 months after בגרות,
bagrus, he's obligated to feed her, which means that's when they should
be getting married, 12 months, not 30 days, 12 months. The גמרא
says אימא בוגרת וששהתה שנים עשר חודש. eima bogeret vesheshahasa shneim asar
chodesh. Change the גירסא. girsa. Have it read, a בוגרת, bogeret, meaning
a woman who's hit בגרות bagrus and it's been 30 days, or
a case of 12 months, but not a case of בוגרת. bogeret.
רבי אליעזר אומר הואיל ובעלה חייב במזונותיה יפר. Rabbi Eliezer omer ho'il
u'va'ala chayav bimzonoseiha yafer. Again, not at all פשט. pshat. We're don't
worry, we're going to reject it. תא שמע, ta shma, come and
hear. המארס את הבתולה. hama'ares es habesula. A woman who does אירוסין,
eirusin, a man who is מארס ma'ares does אירוסין eirusin with a
woman. בין שתבע הבעל והיא מעכבת, bein shetava habaal vehi me'akeves, whether
the husband was the one who said time to get married and
she's the one that said one minute, I you know, I need
some time, so then we're going to give her 12 months. בין
שתבעה היא bein sheteva'ah hi and now we're finding out that actually
did occur that the woman was able to say to the husband,
"hey buddy, it's time to do the נישואין." nisuin Okay, and she
can actually pressure him to do the נישואין nisuin. within the time.
Maybe she starts wanting to get supported, okay, or whatever reason she
wants the נישואין to take place. ובעל מעכב uvaal me'akev and he's
postponing. So this explicates the משנה. Either side after קידושין kiddushin can
say, "time to do the נישואין." And then the other side is
given 12 months. נותנין לה שנים עשר חודש משעת תביעה. nosin la
shneim asar chodesh misha'as tvia. You give 12 months from that moment.
אבל לא משעת אירוסין. aval lo misha'as eirusin. You do not count
it from the time of אירוסין, eirusin, you count it from the
time that one side said it's time to get married. And now
it says,
ובוגרת הרי היא כתבעוה. ubogeret harei hi k'tvauha. If she hits בגרות,
bagrus, that's like the same as as one of the sides demanding
that they get married. כיצד keitzad and it spells it out. בגרה
יום אחד ונתקדשה נותנין לה שנים עשר חודש. bogra yom echad veniskadsha
nosin la shneim asar chodesh. She hit בגרות bagrus on one day
and then she had
קידושין, kiddushin, you give her 12 months. It's explicit. 12 months from
the time she hits בגרות. bagrus. ולארוסה שלשים יום. ul'arusa shloshim yom.
And if it's a normal case of of an ארוסה, arusa, 30
days. We'll see what we'll see what that means. Let's bracket that
for a moment. But what's important now is it says from the
time of בגרות bagrus you have 12 months. Not 30 days. בגרות
bagrus is similar to one side saying time to get married, but
you have a full 12 months, not 30 days. So the גמרא
says תיובתא דרב הונא תיובתא. tyuvta derav huna tyuvta. That is a
full contradiction of רב הונא. Rav Huna. You see that בגרות bagrus
you have 12 months. מאי לארוסה שלושים יום? mai le'arusa shloshim yom?
What does it mean for an ארוסה arusa you have 30 days?
So אמר רב פפא הכי קאמר. amar rav pappa hachi kama. בוגרת
שעברו עליה שנים עשר חודש בבגרות ונתקדשה. bogeres she'avru aleha shemshasar chodesh
bebagrus veniskadsha.
Let's say a woman is the old ripe age of 13 and
a half. Okay? She's a בוגרת bogeres and it's been 12 months
before, she isn't married yet, she's really getting to be an old
maid, she's 13 and a half, okay? And now she has קידושין.
kiddushin. In this case it's בגרות bagrus and קידושין, kiddushin, but it's
already a year into בגרות. bagrus. So now we gotta get things
moving, you don't want to give her a whole year. In this
case נותנין לה שלושים יום כמאן, nosin la shloshim yom keman, she
only has 30 days, which indicates obviously trying to get married right
around that age of 12, 12 and a half, since the clock
starts ticking at בגרות. bagrus. Okay, certainly בגרות bagrus plus קידושין. kiddushin.
I just want to end by saying first of all we're almost
caught up, so we should be very happy. The other point I
just want to say is that תוספות tosfos points out, one minute
to תוספות. I don't get this. If she's a קטנה, she has
more than 12 months. She can be מעכב meakev the entire period
she's a קטנה. If she's a בוגרת, bogeres, the clock starts ticking
right away. So the only case where it's 12 months is that
she's a נערה, naara. okay? Right, yes? That you need the guy
to demand to get married and that you have 12 months. If
she's a קטנה, you have more than 12 months. If she's a
בוגרת, bogeres, you don't need to demand to get married. So the
only case of the משנה is that she's a נערה. naara But
if she's a נערה naara, and he said let's get married and
the clock started ticking, then six months later she's a בוגרת, bogeres,
right? So then that
should you know how does that sort of you know work in?
So תוספות sort of tries to figure the whole thing out about
whether she hits the בגרות bagrus after the תבועה tavuah or you
know at which stage she's sort of hitting the בגרות. bagrus. But
it's a little complicated because what the גמרא has basically done is
it said קטנה separate, there it's not a month a year, there
she can basically refuse as long as she's a קטנה. And בגרות
bagrus even without תבועה tavuah basically as soon as she hits בגרות
bagrus the clock starts ticking, okay? So the basic scenario in the
משנה is that the תבועה tavuah and the clock of the year
started when she was a נערה, started in that period between 12
and 12 and a half.
All righty,
there we go,
thank you.